[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you describe the Four Noble Truths?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first and foremost, there are four descriptions or four aspects of one insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That insight being freedom from suffering, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're free from suffering, that already implies the knowledge of what suffering is, that already implies the knowledge of what has been causing that suffering, that already implies the knowledge of freedom of suffering, and that already implies knowledge how to maintain that freedom from suffering, that insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or how to develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to maintain, which would basically then result in a complete liberation from all the upākalesa and all the other kind of pollutions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like one, two, three, four, that a person needs to discern one by one.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, that's what, you know, in many suttas is mentioned basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be only, it would only be talked about
[SPEAKER_00]: But the cause of suffering... and cause of suffering is, eh... nothing else, except craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, eh... again, that's something that... that people might read over, and then it would maybe just, like, seem like it's... oh, it's making sense, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, in terms of the direct insight, seeing the craving is suffering, results in liberation from that suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the craving means abandoning the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only reason you crave is because you don't really see it directly, you don't understand it, you haven't discerned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... and, and, yeah, the important aspect is to recognize that whenever there is suffering present, you can then say, be, be, like, be, be, be, sort of, you can induce correctly that the craving must be present because the suffering is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not, eh, oh, I suffer, now I have to look for the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: You call it craving or something else, or also assuming that sometimes something else can be the cause of your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It really needs to be brought down so narrowly and so precisely, whereby you discern when the suffering, the disagreeable, unpleasant feeling that you're resisting, basically, when the suffering is present, means it's because simultaneously with it, there is craving present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The absence of that craving simultaneously means the absence of that suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no delay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can have the direct knowledge of freedom from suffering directly verified for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you cannot suffer amidst suffering, as the Buddha would often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, amidst things that used to make you suffer, the mind cannot suffer now, because there is no more craving in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bit hard to abandon craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to abandon craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sense restraint, virtue, develop to the extent necessary, whereby you start discerning then your mental intentions, whether they're rooted in wholesome, unwholesome, whether they're rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you know that they are, you do not engage in them, you do not tolerate them, you do not entertain them, you do not proliferate, you do not invest in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would basically enable the mind to then not resist the unpleasant feeling, to not indulge the pleasant feeling, to not try to distract itself from a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the mind stops doing that, with the previous knowledge that it has heard from outside through the suttas and right teaching, when the mind stops doing that, with the previous knowledge of what craving is,
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be able to see, ah, this is the absence of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will be able to see right there, ah, there's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'll be also able to understand what that suffering was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the suffering of the past, before he understood the way out, he wouldn't be suffering on account of that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same knowledge would be applying to the present, past and the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, how to endure those painful feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have them now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful feelings, cravings.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you endure them, basically, if instead of enduring, you want to give in to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you want to give in to a will or distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that would result in you having to endure them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes, if you can sort of... you don't have to endure them, without having to give in to sensuality, aversion or delusion, then that's fine as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to just constantly going looking for pain to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will not necessarily result in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, how does one know that it's... you're freer from craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that you... Because there's no suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no suffering because you cannot suffer, not because you're hiding away from it, or because you're not... you're just avoiding things that would... that would use to... that would use... that used to cause you to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like, avoiding things means you're afraid of something already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, say, I don't know, a person doesn't leave their kuti because they don't want to talk to anyone because it might annoy them and then they'll suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just protecting their precarious environment of non-disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you must protect it means you're disturbed by that, which means they're not truly not suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just hiding away from the greater extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to reckon... that's why, like, you know, eh... a consciousness monk, he doesn't neglect his duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, certain things that you must do, they are not necessarily connected just... just sitting in a solitude and practicing, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like here, we live by ourselves, we do things ourselves, so we... we, you know, we have to go and fix the water line.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to go and patch my tank.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I don't have to, but then I won't have any water.
[SPEAKER_00]: But having to do that doesn't bother you either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeking out it as a distraction, but you're not running away from it when it arises on its own as something that's necessary to be done to sustain the way you live it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you need to have, again, that self-honesty, so you know you're not hiding away, you're not indulging, you're not covering anything up.
[SPEAKER_00]: With that self-honesty, and all the restraint of the senses, seeing the danger in the slightest fault, moderation in eating, that would result just in obviously being mindful of your actions, you start discerning mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning them, basically, the mind is already developing a certain perspective, because there is no craving without intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is intention without craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arahant can still intend, and decide, and choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he has no craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to see that, you have to see the intentions to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most people are not even aware of the mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think intention is just the most obvious choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just little inclinations, thoughts in themselves, that are already intentional.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's subtler.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order to reach the subtle level, this whole sense restraint, restrained by the patimokkha, by the virtue, moderation, idiocy and mindfulness, it's not... it's absolutely necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unnegotiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And with the right instruction and the right way of looking, that's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the right instruction, it is just restraint, which is good, but it doesn't lead you to any knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But with the right instruction and that, that's all you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes people might think, okay, the restraint is not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they would think, okay, well, now I got the dhamma, so I don't have to restrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, dhamma applies only where the restraint is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can see,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, restraint is not the dhamma, as in the application of the dhamma is not the same as the the necessary basis for that application, but you wouldn't be able to apply it if there is no necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind practices like that, then the
[SPEAKER_00]: The inclination in form of craving is becoming more and more obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you start recognizing that there are certain ways when you intend and incline, it makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes you feel too much, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes you too involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exposes you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes you liable.
[SPEAKER_00]: By discerning those things, you stop intending like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not intending like that, you're not perpetuating the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in terms of feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always in relation to feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in an agreeable feeling that is present, you have to sort of discern the inclination towards wanting more of it, or towards wanting to stay longer, towards wanting to not go away so soon, towards wanting to increase it, to intensify it, to prolong it, any of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a disagreeable feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: It could be the general disagreeable mood, or something more specific.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to remove, or rather discern, and by discerning you remove it automatically, the inclination towards resisting it, towards trying to find a justification for it, towards trying to find an explanation for it, towards psychologizing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just any of those things are mechanisms which you try to engage in, so to remove it, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the subtlest of them is the neutral feeling, when it's neither pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when people give in to distraction, delusion, indolence, laziness, like mental heedlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't do any of those three things, you're not perpetuating craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the same time, you've got to be able to... to feel, to be aware of your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent that they have a reason on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because feelings arise having a reason, they cease on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not saying that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to be... again, that's what mindfulness of feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning the nature, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing that they have arisen on their own, this pleasant experience at the moment is arisen on its own, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't keep...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of it, because pleasure means craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaning too much towards that pleasure means craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaning away from the disagreeable means craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaning towards forgetfulness and distraction and
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaning towards forgetfulness and distraction, that means craving in the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really being aware of those leanings towards feelings... Yeah, that's a good way to start.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't like having... oh, this is my craving, because craving is in your attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can... you can... you can bring it down so precisely, whereby you would see the... the... the... either the presence of suffering, or the presence of the possibility to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of those is generated by the amount of your leaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're automatically generating possibility... liability to suffering, which is in itself dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use that to know whether you lean or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognition of how liable to suffering does this make you.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no method that can show you that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because method is on the level almost like bodily action or certainly bodily perceptions where you're just sort of perceiving or going through some motions.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is... we're talking about intentions behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever method you do, you have to look at the intention behind, which means method becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means method is your sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Method is your sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's as close as to method as you can get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Method is your moderation in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shabu.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about, you know, noting every every movement of your mind, quickly write it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely misplaced, looking at the wrong place, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not seeing your intention to note.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you couldn't be noting your intention to note.
[SPEAKER_00]: Noting is an action which is already intended, which is already leaned towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're not seeing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not seeing that, no amount of engaging in that action will reveal its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, the Buddha would have given a method and described it in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they did ask him what's the direct method, he said, a young man develops faith, leaves his home, lives restrained by the rules of patimokkha, practices sense restraint, sees the danger in the slightest fault, moderate in eating and devotes his time, basically, to wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: First watch of the night, second watch of the night, third watch of the night, and then he understands that the rebirth has been sort of destroyed, and I remember the first time I read that as a layman, I was also looking for a method.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought, well, this is just too general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why wouldn't he just give you a particular recipe how to become enlightened?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there isn't any.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the most particular you can get.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not seeing it in a direct manner, it's just because all the wrong views that are on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to meet that Buddha's instruction halfway, basically, or even two-thirds of the way, to start to make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if person don't change any view, then they just add on top of their views, their notion of other practices, that's that's what you get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Methods and modern vipassana techniques and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or methods of concentration and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to look at the intention behind actions and you can't concentrate on that, because it's behind your concentration.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can discern it, you can know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's said the consciousness is to be fully understood, not concentrated on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't be aware of your intentions all the time?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can be aware in that peripheral background manner, but awareness and concentration, in terms of techniques, is not the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are not aware when they're doing meditation technique, quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're practicing some sort of focusing exercise on one thing or the other, which means there's no general awareness there.
[SPEAKER_01]: To have been able to see your intentions...
[SPEAKER_00]: They can only be seen indirectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: By the way you are... whatever you're choosing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can only be seen indirectly on the basis of your sense restraint and sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see them indirectly if you're unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, yeah, you can have a notion of it to some extent, but, like, understanding the nature to, like, having adding that clarity generated to the point of being able to fully discern it, you won't have that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like trying to collect the water in, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_00]: A ten meter deep pool, tank, with just constantly punching hole at the bottom of it, so it will never fill up to the bottom... to the top.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you need to have it filled up, basically.